Guide to the Aaron Siskind photographs of Harlem, circa 1933-1941 RL.11171
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Aaron Siskind photographs of Harlem
circa 1933-1941
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Archive of Documentary Arts (Duke University)
Siskind, Aaron
RL.11171
1.0 Linear Feet 1 box 28 photographic prints
Aaron Siskind (1903-1991) was an American photographer and faculty member of the Chicago Institute of Design and Rhode Island School of Design. Collection consists of 28 black-and-white signed prints by Siskind, documenting life in New York City's Harlem neighborhoods from about 1933 to 1941. The images form part of two projects, "Harlem document" and "The most crowded block in the world," and feature portraits of African American men, women, and children; street scenes; images from the Apollo and Lafayette theaters, a night club, and a church; and the interiors and exteriors of tenement buildings. The gelatin silver prints measure 11x14 inches. Some of the images have two copies in the collection, resulting in 23 unique images represented by 28 prints. Acquired as part of the Archive of Documentary Arts at Duke University.
Print versos are marked with legacy identifiers, titles and dates assigned by former owners, and other notes.
Arrangement
The prints are arranged in chronological order.
Biographical Note
Aaron Siskind (1903-1991) was a New York City-based photographer, and faculty member of the Chicago's Institute of Design at the Illinois Institute of Technology; later in life, he joined his mentor Henry Callahan at the Rhode Island School of Design until he retired in the 1970s.
Conditions Governing Access
Collection is open for research.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The Aaron Siskind photographs of Harlem were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in 2015 and 2020.
Collection Overview
Collection consists of 28 black-and-white photographs taken during the earliest years of Aaron Siskind's career, documenting life and conditions in New York City's Harlem neighborhoods from about 1933 to 1941. The majority of the images feature portraits of African American men, women, and children in various settings: on the street; in the Apollo and Lafayette theaters; in a night club; taking part in a church service; playing around abandoned houses; and posing in bedrooms, kitchens, and other interior rooms of tenement buildings. A few images focus only on buildings or outdoor settings.
Siskind included these and other images in two photo projects in which he played a central role: "Harlem document" and "The most crowded block in the world." "Harlem document" was sponsored by the Photo League of New York. The second project unfolded from about 1939 to 1941 after Siskind left the Photo League; to a large extent, this project carried on his work of documenting street life in Harlem.
The gelatin silver prints in this collection are all signed by Siskind. They all measure 11x14 inches, with the image dimensions ranging from 9 1/8 x 8 3/4 to 11 3/4 x 9 7/5 inches. The year these particular prints were created is unknown. Some of the images have two copies in the collection, resulting in 23 unique images represented by 28 prints. Library staff assigned titles and original negative dates according to original negatives donated by Siskind to the Eastman House; some titles are not known. Titles assigned by a former collector, sometimes present on the back of the prints, are also given in a note field in the entry for each print.
Related Materials
James Van Der Zee photographs, circa 1908-1935
African American churches -- New York (State) -- New York -- Photographs; African American theater -- New York (State) -- New York -- Photographs; African Americans -- New York (State) -- New York; African Americans -- New York (State) -- New York -- Social conditions -- 20th century; African Americans -- New York (State) -- New York -- Social life and customs -- 20th century; African Americans -- Photographs; African Americans -- Portraits; Apollo Theater (New York, N.Y.: 125th Street) -- Photographs; New Lafayette Theatre -- Photographs; Documentary Photography -- New York (State) -- Harlem (New York, N.Y.); Photographers -- New York (State) -- New York; Street photography -- New York (State) -- New York; Harlem (New York, N.Y.) -- Photographs; Harlem (New York, N.Y.) -- Social conditions -- 20th century; Harlem (New York, N.Y.) -- Social life and customs -- 20th century; New York (N.Y.) -- Photographs; Black-and-white photographs; Gelatin silver prints; Archive of Documentary Arts (Duke University); Siskind, Aaron
- Head, circa 1933; Gelatin silver print. Sheet size: 14 x 11 inches; image size: 9 1/16 x 8 1/2 inches. (Box 1, Folder 1, Print RL.11171-P-0001)
  Scope and Contents
  Title and date assigned by collector: Boy's head, 1932.
- Boys in empty tenement, Harlem, 1935; Gelatin silver print. Sheet size: 13 7/8 x 10 7/8 inches; image size: 9 1/4 x 7 1/4 inches. (Box 1, Folder 20, Print RL.11171-P-0025)
  Title and date derived from print verso.
- Girl with clothes form, Harlem, 1937; Gelatin silver print. Sheet size: 14 x 10 7/8 inches; image size: 11 x 7 7/8 inches. (Box 1, Folder 20, Print RL.11171-P-0026)
- Kitchen scene, Harlem, circa 1937; Gelatin silver print. Sheet size: 13 7/8 x 10 7/8 inches; image size: 9 7/8 x 7 5/8 inches. (Box 1, Folder 20, Print RL.11171-P-0027)
- Condemned house, circa 1937-1940; Gelatin silver print. Sheet size: 14 x 11 inches; image size: 9 1/8 x 7 1/4 inches. (Box 1, Folder 1, Print RL.11171-P-0002)
- Condemned house, circa 1937-1940; Gelatin silver print. Sheet size: 14 x 11 inches; image size: 9 1/8 x 7 1/4 inches. (Box 1, Folder 2, Print RL.11171-P-0003)
  Collector's title: Boys in empty tenement.
- Bootblacks, circa 1937-1940; Gelatin silver print. Sheet size: 14 x 11 inches; image size: 10 3/8 x 7 3/4 inches. (Box 1, Folder 3, Print RL.11171-P-0004)
  Collector's title: Street scene 4.
- Wishing tree, circa 1937-1940; Gelatin silver print. Sheet size: 11 x 14 inches; image size: 6 5/8 x 10 1/8 inches. (Box 1, Folder 4, Print RL.11171-P-0005)
- Wishing tree, circa 1937-1940; Gelatin silver print. Sheet size: 11 x 14 inches; image size: 6 5/8 x 10 1/8 inches. (Box 1, Folder 4, Print RL.11171-P-0006)
- Brothers, circa 1937-1940; Gelatin silver print. Sheet dimensions: 14 x 11 inches; image dimensions: 10 x 7 1/8 inches. (Box 1, Folder 5, Print RL.11171-P-0007)
- Brothers, circa 1937-1940; Gelatin silver print. Sheet dimensions: 14 x 11 inches; image dimensions: 10 x 7 1/8 inches. (Box 1, Folder 5, Print RL.11171-P-0008)
- Storeroom, there's a rat in there, circa 1937-1940; Gelatin silver print. Sheet size: 14 x 11 inches; image size: 11 x 7 7/8 inches. (Box 1, Folder 6, Print RL.11171-P-0009)
- Storeroom, there's a rat in there, circa 1937-1940; Gelatin silver print. Sheet size: 14 x 11 inches; image size: 11 x 7 7/8 inches. (Box 1, Folder 6, Print RL.11171-P-0010)
- Cabaret strip dancer, circa 1937; Gelatin silver print. Sheet size: 14 x 11 inches; image size: 10 1/2 x 7 7/8 inches. (Box 1, Folder 7, Print RL.11171-P-0011)
  Collector's title: Night club 1, Harlem.
- Amateur performer, Apollo Theater, circa 1937; Gelatin silver print. Sheet size: 14 x 11 inches; image size: 9 1/4 x 7 1/8 inches. (Box 1, Folder 8, Print RL.11171-P-0012)
- Lafayette Theatre, circa 1937-1940; Gelatin silver print. Sheet size: 14 x 11 inches; image size: 11 3/4 x 8 5/8 inches. (Box 1, Folder 9, Print RL.11171-P-0013)
  Collector's title: Lafayette Theater 1, Harlem.
- Lafayette Theatre soldier, circa 1938; Gelatin silver print. Sheet size: 14 x 11 inches; image size: 11 3/4 x 8 3/4 inches. (Box 1, Folder 10, Print RL.11171-P-0014)
  Collector's title: Lafayette Theater soldier, Harlem.
- Church singer, circa 1937-1940; Gelatin silver print. Sheet size: 11 x 14 inches; image size: 8 5/8 x 12 inches. (Box 1, Folder 11, Print RL.11171-P-0015)
- Church singer, circa 1937-1940; Gelatin silver print. Sheet size: 11 x 14 inches; image size: 8 5/8 x 12 inches. (Box 1, Folder 11, Print RL.11171-P-0016)
- No known title, circa 1940-1941; Gelatin print. Sheet size: 14 x 11 inches; image size: 9 5/8 x 8 1/2 inches. (Box 1, Folder 12, Print RL.11171-P-0017)
  Collector's title: Street scene 2, Harlem. Forms part of the project "The most crowded block in the world."
- Backyard, circa 1937-1940; Gelatin print. Sheet size: 14 x 11 inches; image size: 11 x 7 3/4 inches. (Box 1, Folder 13, Print RL.11171-P-0018)
- Narrow court, circa 1940; Gelatin silver print. Sheet size: 14 x 11 inches; image size: 11 3/4 x 8 1/4 inches. (Box 1, Folder 14, Print RL.11171-P-0019)
  Collector's title: Airshaft, Harlem.
- Street scene 1, Harlem, 1940; Gelatin silver print. Sheet size: 14 x 10 7/8 inches; image size: 9 1/4 x 8 5/8 inches. (Box 1, Folder 20, Print RL.11171-P-0028)
- No known title, circa 1940-1941; Gelatin silver print. Sheet size: 14 x 11 inches; image size: 10 7/8 x 7 7/8 inches. (Box 1, Folder 15, Print RL.11171-P-0020)
  Collector's title: Bedroom through doorway, Harlem. Forms part of the project "The most crowded block in the world," also shot in Harlem.
- No known title, circa 1940-1941; Gelatin silver print. Sheet size: 11 x 14 inches; image size: 8 5/8 x 12 inches. (Box 1, Folder 16, Print RL.11171-P-0021)
  Collector's title: Man in bed, Harlem. Forms part of project, "The most crowded block in the world."
- No known title, 1940; Gelatin silver print. Sheet size: 14 x 11 inches; image size: 11 x 8 inches. (Box 1, Folder 17, Print RL.11171-P-0022)
  Collector's title: Lady and lamp, Harlem. Forms part of project, "The most crowded block in the world," also shot in Harlem.
- No known title, circa 1940-1941; Gelatin silver print. Sheet size: 14 x 11 inches; image size: 11 x 8 inches. (Box 1, Folder 18, Print RL.11171-P-0023)
  Collector's title: Man with lamp, Harlem. Forms part of the project, "The most crowded block in the world."
- No known title, circa 1940-1941; Gelatin silver print. Sheet size: 14 x 11 inches; image size: 9 1/2 x 8 1/2 inches. (Box 1, Folder 19, Print RL.11171-P-0024)
  Collector's title: Man by bed, Harlem. Forms part of the project, "The most crowded block in the world."